Serpent's Tooth

Andre Norton

The haze was thinner than a drifting cloud, moving with the travelers... was no rain here to temper the burning of the rough soil under Rentam's bare and already scarred feet.  Modic rode, even in this time and place he held to the dignity of a Seeker, but the trembling legs of the bony horse he bestrode (it was the worst mount of his train) threatened any moment to collapse, spilling rider on the ground.  Only the Seeker's will kept the horse going along a wandering seam in the surface of the stones they had chanced upon an hour ago.

In Rentam coiled and wove the old fears which had been bred in his kind for generations.  He had been sure of disaster to come ever since this thin-faced man, with a jaw and nose which had the side view of a sword, had come to the village to demand, with a certainty overriding all other wills, a guide for journey west.  Neither had Modic followed the rules of the Betweener village but had stabbed with a gloved forefinger at Rentam and called for him.

Though Sequine, the Speaker, had argued it was not the tall youth's turn.

Modic had only grinned fiercely and shaken his head when the first two drawn properly by lot came to him, saying that Rentam looked sturdy enough to lead a Traveler into the Questionable Land.  At last Sequine had shrugged and nodded.  Each of them knew sooner or later a guide found the Gate of Death.  Now women and children hid in the mud-brick huts as all had heard of Betweeners slain for drunken amusement, or because would-be Seekers had been irritated by some small matter.  From the moment Modic had made his choice they knew that it was Rentam who must go.

A half company of riders appearing on the bluff above had been an open warning for the clan village to obey Modic's desires.

"No knife."  The Seeker had ridden closer to inspect the guide's equipment which Sequine's own son had brought forth.  Modic kicked out as the boy passed him with such skill that the knife, a little loose in the scabbard, flew to strike against a hut wall.

"Leave it, you!"  Modic moved his mount again until it stood between the Speaker and the boy.  The Seeker said no more, but Rentam nodded to the Speaker.

"Obey ... for the good of the clan."

In that last moment of boyhood the guide lost belief that truth and right were strong against any evil which might prevail.  Now to be separated from his own people had only one meaning .. . this doom-faced warrior had a secret, and surely no one would live to betray its discovery.  There were his men beyond; might he be able to get rid of them as easily?

"You pledge yourself..  ."  That was no question.  More like an order. Rentam nodded.  He could sense the tension seep out of the rest of the villagers.  A bargain had been struck and surely this one, who knew so much of their customs, would now leave.  It was unfortunate about

Rentam of course, but he had no kin here closer than a cousin, and between them had been many quarrels.  What was the life of one man compared to all the village?

They had set out at the first color of sunrise and had kept plodding on straight into the heart of the vast waste.  The now risen sun pressed a blanket of heat down upon them.  They all carried water gourds which they had filled at the village spring.  Yes, Rentam thought, watching them when he believed Modic no longer checked upon him, these were indeed Seekers.  Certainly they used water frugally at the rest stops Modic ordered each time the shadows of the towering stones standing here and there lengthened appreciatively.

Also they watered their beasts, first giving them to drink out of their helms and washing out the nostrils of each with a damp cloth.  For themselves they allowed only what must have been a swallow or two.

Hereabouts the desert land was not still flat for there appeared a way which ran straight as if that had been cut by the force of man's desire for a road.  Curiosity awakened in Rentam.  At the third stop he pretended to adjust the webbing which held his water gourd and packet of journey food, while, with his left hand, he stabbed one of his long and narrow fingers into the sand and gravel, far enough to scrape against the webbing of flesh which united all six fingers into a more solid fist.  Underneath there was indeed a solid obstruction.  Two of his middle fingers met a solid surface with bruising force.

Now he pulled his sun-resisting cloak higher on his shoulders and, through narrowed eyes, surveyed the country.  Here stood a third hill, a mount of stone, partly seen there some summer dried shrubs... Yes! Rentam's breath puffed against the edge of his cloak as straightaway he fought a sharp stab of emotion which he must not allow any of those about him to see.

Even the guides knew very little of this dreary world ... save of the paths to which one or two bolder explorers might add a few new lengths several times in a lifetime.  He knew that hill right enough ... it marked the furthermost of his own rovings in this direction.  Now, as

he sighted it, he believed that this curious sand covered cut ran directly towards that, as if the hill was indeed a marker on an ancient road.

It could lead where?  Still aware of Modic he turned his head slowly, this time seemingly concentrating on the shoulder strapping of his supply net.  He was somehow sure that he was right.  They had camped on a portion of a forgotten road which ran straight ahead.

Rentam's pointed tongue slid over his lower lip as if, like his very distant cousin of the true lizard breed, he could pick up scent impressions cast by man or animal.

One kept away from these roads.  Such could be traced easily enough, but they led to the spirit places where the haze, such as they had traveled through earlier, thickened to give shelter to things... things which he had heard described, legends of all guide villages.  He slid his tongue out between his lips, startled past prudence into a grunt.

Could the Seeker know of this?  Was he now aware that such roads led to the death light?  A shadow fell across his face as he watched, Modic, wondering for a moment of real fear if the man had guessed at his own discovery.

The Seeker dropped to the sand and crossed his legs, his hands playing with the hilt of his sword, drawing the blade out an inch or two from the scabbard and then thrusting it forcefully back again, as if he foresaw a need for its use.  Rentam had regained full control... he could hear the snick of the blade, however his narrow gaze was on Modic's face not the Seeker's hands.  It was always the eyes into which one must look, Rentam remembered clearly Sequine's warning.  For it is by the changes in a man's eyes one could read the coming of violence.

"So," Modic's voice was hardly above a whisper, certainly it could not reach anyone farther away then Rentam, "you have found it.  Dig!"  His lazy tone sharpened into an order, he motioned toward where the guide had been secretly delving.  Obeying, Rentam dug both-handed now. Within a number of breaths, lightly drawn breaths (lest he could take into him some danger of this place), he scooped out parched earth, throwing it to one side.  He was right, it required very little in the way of labor to lay bare a section of a road of the waste devils.." the black surface of it un corroded by time and as smooth as his own scratched and bleeding skin.

Though Modic leaned more closely forward, Rentam perceived he did not lose sight of the guide for more than half a breath at a time.

"Right."  When the Seeker spoke it seemed more to himself than to Rentam.

"The road to Lonscraft... at last!"

This time Rentam's astonishment was rooted in fear.  He jerked back his hands from hand contact with the damnable thing.  Fighting to remain impassive, knowing within him that Modic was well aware of his inbred fear and was now studying the Betweener closely, a small evil smile about his lips.

"Ah, yes."  The Seeker kept his voice low and confidential in tone, as if he and Rentam shared some secret which was unknown to the others.

"This is the way to Lonscraft.  Though that was not the name it bore in other days when the world was still all for men and not for sand-dwelling rats!"

He scrabbled inside his outer robe with his left hand, bringing out a small sheet of dull metal, near as thin as the skin of a ripe wavel. Still keeping one finger firmly on the edge of it he pushed the plate a little closer to Rentam.

"Do you know the reading of maps, Guide, or do you only carry such information in your scaled head?"  His slight smile now held no amusement, rather cruel, taunting humor.

So this one did not know of those treasure places located by villages... to which the youths went to learn ... by heart and deep in the mind ... the ancient roads and more than roads, the dangers and few secrets of the Sand Sea.  One quick glance told Rentam much.  That which Modic held must have been graven by a master worker in metal. However only as far as the hillock behind them now did the lines assume any kinship with the records he himself had long ago memorized.  This map displayed the warning blue of the Before Time road leading to a city of even darker blue, a color which seemed to pulsate in the light as if a breathing, and perhaps sentient, creature.

"Well, and what have you to say to this, Guide?  I needed your steering to that hillock, knowing that what I sought lay beyond."

Dry as it was, a droplet of saliva gathered at the corner of the Seeker's mouth, as he no longer gazed at Rentam ... rather at his map.

It was the colors which confused the sight, Rentam decided.

Certainly those lines did not really coil or quiver.  From which clan had Modic stolen this record ... one of the forbidden ones used to warn?

"It is true!"  There was a sharp note in the man's voice as if Rentam had openly questioned that fact.

"Lonscraft lies awaiting us."

"That is a death place," Rentam replied evenly.

"He who rashly adventures into one of those gathers to him an ill for which there is no treatment.  His skin rots upon his body, pain wrings him to death.  There is nothing worth such a death ... all the Betweeners know that."

Modic laughed, "Guide, you and your kind have been content to exist for years on the border of this demon-haunted land with no reason for it. Every illness runs its course and then disappears.

Have you not heard of the burning fever which may strike out of nowhere for a season and then be utterly gone ... or the Great Cough which has devastated whole cities, such as Quaadad, yet men may, live there in comfort now.  There is no death which lingers forever ... especially in a desert city where there is naught to feed its hunger.  Long ago Lonscraft must have been deserted even by demons.  Yet there still lies within its walls secrets...."  The fingers of his hand clenched over the map as if he would pluck what he wished from the surface.

"Riches beyond richness.  Guide think on it!"

Riches, of course, were what had drawn this Seeker and his following of ragged men (who, nevertheless, carried well-kept arms) into the desert. How many such maps had been shown briefly to the Betweeners in the generations since they had begun their very cautious ventures into the parched land?  Rentam knew that it was not in the inner walls of Lonscraft which he himself feared, but perhaps the fact that he knew too much now.  He guessed that Modic, on the threshold of what he thought an exciting and profitable discovery, would not parade and plume himself before his rag-tag crew.  No, but he might talk freely before one who was destined never to come out of the Forgotten land. That sword which the Seeker held so tightly would put an end to any chance of another's betrayal.  Not that Rentam would fare better than any one of the men clinging to the shadows about them, seeking for some small answer to the burning of the sun.  Murder was the practical move for Modic, and the Betweener already accepted the drastic end before him.

The Seeker would use him (in spite of that map) to follow the ancient way.... He might even test the authenticity of legends by dispatching Rentam alone into the midst of a dead city perhaps as bait to spring a trap.

One slight figure, cloaked against the heat, stood alone here.

However, the death blow had not yet been openly delivered.

Though every breath Rentam drew brought him closer to that time of challenge.

Warnings known to his own kind worked in him.  With those a small spark of excitement flashed into life, turning his thoughts in another direction.  If this Modic was right and he could win through to return with such knowledge for his own clan ... I Their own perilous situation

might cease to be.  There were other "cities" each reported to the Seeker..  . and the information was shared with two other villages within a three days' walking.  No longer would they have to point these arrogant and cruel Seekers to the Dry Land, instead they would venture inward for their own loot and trade their findings openly at the Mus-fair, year's end.  As long as Modic made no outward attack Rentam would serve his own people, forcing into his memory a picture of here in relation to the hill point.  However he must also watch for a chance of escape.  It would indeed be strange ... even without belief... that one of the guides could be tracked and captured traveling a country he knew well.  Though he had kept his advance with Modic to a shambling trot which matched the pace of the bone rack of a horse ... he could summon the speed of his far, far kin, tailed and going four footed here. Let him but get Modic thoroughly interested in something other than himself..  . say, a forgotten treasure house .. . and Rentam could slip away before anyone here could use lance or sword.  The one thing he had to fear (bow bolts) was lacking among the troops.

He must play a perilous game.  His thought, as well as his body, was intentionally slow.

"You seek a great treasure?"  he asked, apparently taking no interest in the Seeker's hand upon the sword hilt.

Modic showed his yellow stained teeth in a wider grin.

"Treasure?  Yes, but not perhaps quite as you and those ..."  he gestured to his men with his chin, "would so see it."  Then he snapped his jaws shut and scowled at Rentam and the others with narrow measurement, as if, of a sudden he regretted the revelation of even so little.

"You are a guide."  He changed the subject abruptly.

"Let us now see that vaunted power of such talent beyond the boundaries.

Get me to Lonscraft or within sight of it before that sun is gone.

He gave a quick glance over his shoulder as if to measure where in the sky the light-giving ball now rode.

"There are many cities .. ."  Rentam said quietly.

"It can well be that this trail," once more he patted the sand about that pocket in which lay the traces of the very ancient way, "could lead somewhere else than Lonscraft."

There came a sharp bark of laughter from the other.

"No, it is here!"  He had picked up his bit of engraved metal and thrust it back into hiding.

"I have been long at this game, Guide, but not so long as to become weary and make such an error.  Ten times over have I come across the Between lands... and more times than that have I listened to the tales told at Mus-fair.  First, that hillock which you have found for us is

pointing to Lonscraft."

Rentam blinked, he had indeed believed that the Seeker was an old hand at the game of invading the uninvadable.  But what could keep one of a sane mind so long at searching?  It was true that the hill behind them was relatively unknown.  He, himself, had chanced upon it only last

season... it had been his first addition to the clan lore.  However there were signs of others who visited there .. . horse dung dried into powder where the wind rolled it here and there, some scrapes on one of the upstanding stones which were too regular to be of natural fashioning and which Modic had studied with care as long as there was light enough to see both last night and again early this morning. Messages?

The clan no longer wrote such notes.  He would report again what he had seen so that mention was made of it in the training of the young.  Who needed scratches set on rocks when he could summon into memory ... full and vivid as any picture ... what he had seen over Modic's hunched

shoulder?

The Seeker made no protest against Rentam's watching.

Though when one of his own men came near he had lashed out at him with a barbed tongue and an order which was to be obeyed.

Another reason for Rentam to nourish his own belief that to find Lonscraft would mean his death.  In fact he had wondered why that had not yet come.  Modic had his road well ready to follow.

What more did he want from Rentam?

The Seeker swung around to give a hoarse, rallying cry which brought up the heads of his men, summoned their attention.  He loped towards them at a curious one-sided, limping walk which was his pace when dismounted, meeting them part way.  His own mount stood head hanging as others were saddled and made ready to ride.

Modic still bestrode the poorest of the lot, Rentam noted, his eyes more than half shaded by wrinkled, greenish lids.  Why such a choice, and why was Modic waving his men on that straight line which was the work of the ancients?  Why would Modic share a treasure find with those

ragged and brutish riders at all?  Rentam did not doubt in the least that Modic could have found some other track for them to follow.  Yet he stood there, watching them ride on, as Rentam rose to his feet behind him.  They were indeed swinging into the trail Modic indicated.

One, at least, had wit enough to be suspicious.  He called out something in one of the complicated river languages, reining back his horse, his closest comrades drawing in about him.

"Na ... Na ..."  Modic raised bare hands in a gesture meant to reassure, following his denial with a stream of speech, each word gliding close to the one before it so that Rentam could not begin to pick out the few he knew .. . except one "treasure" ... perhaps that was akin in meaning in every speech, because it was a universal cry to action.  Though for a moment or two it looked as if this one rider was not easily convinced, though those who had gathered about him fell into eager talk with much gesturing of hands and licking of lips.  At length he, too, grunted, the bush of filthy hair on his cheeks and chin stretching as he made a spitting motion into the sand.  Though it was plain he had no excess liquid to so void.

Modic lingered, fussing with his horse's gear as if making sure all was in good order... in the mean time giving quick glances at the men riding, two together, down that defile which marked the road.  As the last one passed another dune some distance away, he spoke again to

Rentam.

"What is the threat which keeps you and your kind from such places open for looting?  I have seen pieces of ancient metal, gems, and even bits of carvings offered for sale.  Yet upon the asking they will always say that such was found in some miserable small ruin.

Have you never tried for Pospfer or Wejn or perhaps Slasta?"

Rentam hoped he controlled his surprise well.  Why did this Seeker mark down the three worst cities of the old tales, places where in lay death in waiting?

"Such are cursed," he replied shortly.

"The abodes of demons, eh?"  Once again Modic showed his teeth in a grin.

"How know you that it is not the dead themselves who rise to defend what they once held?  What tales do your Speakers tell of these lands? That they were conquered one by one by a fearsome enemy?  If that be so where is that enemy now?  No tale of such an invasion has ever been told.  Why strike your people at one portion of the land only?"

"These be the riddles all share, Seeker," answered Rentam.  He was on his feet, testing the cord of the net which held his supplies.

"Legend says the death rode from the sky on a forked flame and where that touched the ground there was ruin and nothingness..  ..

The dead do not live to fight for what was once theirs.  But the breath of the dying clings to the cities.  A man breathes in that which will shrivel his lungs, and stands against the unseen which will eat the flesh from his bones.  Some times even now a reckless far rover dies

so."

Modic fingered his bristled chin with two grimy fingers, staring after the disappearing men of his party.

"Breath of death..."  he repeated slowly.

"Then we shall at least prove that right or wrong."  From one of his saddle bags he pulled two cloths, the metallic smell of leif about them both.  One he tossed to Rentam who automatically caught it.  He watched Modic hang his cap on the saddle horn of his horse, shake out the material to pull it like a bag over his head.  There were holes for eyes, and where the mouth would be a slit covered by a mesh woven of shining threads.  Somewhat clumsily the guide followed the Seeker's action.

The heavy odor which appeared to waft from the material was so pungent that he began to cough and would have taken off the thing if Modic had not caught him by the wrist.

"Leave be, Betweener.  That which you smell is a mighty spell against all which fills the air.  I paid a full year of swording caravans to get those ... and had a heavy argument into the bargain.  There only lives one in the river land who makes such now.  He works from a very old picture and notes of how it is done .. . and those he will share with none.  Still Amers of Klydul, wearing one of these, did ride the streets of Maksheeff and returned alone of his company."

"To die ten days later screaming that a demon within him gnawed at his heart," replied Rentam.

"Yes, we have heard the full of that tale."

"Only his demon was a potion brewed by his own second wife, that she might set hand on what he had brought back but would show to no one, saying that it was worth the war ransom of at least five lords.  Also he intended to take it to the Fire of Venex for an auction," Modic returned coolly.

"It was not his travels which killed him ... only his own foolish tongue for he told wide and far just what he had gained."

The last of the riders disappeared around an upstanding rock spur, and now Modic swung into the saddle and flicked his riding lash at Rentam as a sharp-edged order to move.  The guide was well able to match the ambling gait Modic's horse approved, it seemed that the Seeker must

still be in quest of landmarks.  However he and Rentam followed the same path as those others.

Yet their rest had lasted longer than even Rentam had noted.

Now shadows crept out from the rocks and the chill of the open night, as the baking sun set, loosing winds which carried cold out of the western unknown.  The far mountains were only distant blots against a graying sky.  No guide had ever struck as far as to climb those.  If

ever a Seeker had gone there he had not returned.  Rentam pulled his cloak tidily about him and thought of the Seeker again and the tale which threatened all who were with him.

If Modic had even been to Maksheeff that was on a dream supplied by a night demon.  Rentam padded on tirelessly and thought of demons. During his own few years and his strikes into the Dry Country he had never seen a demon.  Nor had anyone in his village back to the first foray

accounts of their clan's coming, which Jawser the Blind kept counted in his bundle of remembering knots.  Demons were talked of often ... but they were never seen.

Rentam had come to think that they must be totally invisible.  Yet the Speakers who had the freedom of Above and Below had not reported them either.  Thus they indeed might... if they still existed ... be able to shelter themselves on more than one level of dream seeing.  That such would lurk in the dire, broken cities moldered half away by time was reasonable enough.

He felt a sickness gathering at the back of his mouth, born of the stuff in which his mask was steeped.  Now he tried to raise the banding from his throat and spat a glob of greenish phlegm to the rock beside him.

"Keep that mask on, you young fool!"  Modic's words were muffled but could be heard.

"See where we now stand, and you would give the ill which lies in waiting here a chance to get at you!"

The rock against which he spat he could see now through the dulling light of late afternoon, was not virgin stone but rather a tongue of what might be a buried building, pointed skyward.  It was fashioned of small stones fitted together so that the cracks of their joining were

difficult to see.  On the other side of the road was a second such hill; the width between certainly measured a space of entrance which might once have stood as a gate to a road four or five times as wide as those which were known outside the Dry Land.

Some of the sand was disturbed here, moved to show under red earth like unto any field where the keeps had little access to irrigation.

Where this appeared it was churned and marked by the horsemen who had proceeded them.

Also they could hear voices from ahead where the piers of stone grew higher and even turned into a wall which ran true for more than just a stride or two.  Modic's men were gathered there, all ahorse, gazing about them as if they were not really prepared for this.

Ahead of them the walls arose abruptly.  While there were cracks in them, they were not tumbled across the road.  Those led to taller walls ... to buildings like unto towers such as Rentam had seen in ruin all along the border, as if erected hastily to help defend against what might come from the Dry Lands.  These were broken here and there, after no regular pattern, by narrow slits which must have been intended to give watch sites for defenders.

Here, too, there was a difference.  The sun had gone far enough down its sky trail now to lengthen shadows greatly.  Only these were no honest shadows such as a man could trust with his eyes.  For from those wall slots leaked a defused blue light, thin, haze like not unlike, save in color, to that haze which locked trails in the dawn hours.

The men had stopped where four roads came together and there was an open space centered by an oval which was curbed waist high, perhaps in order that none could fall within its circumference.

From that also curled, in wisps like the lazy curls of a smoking fire, bluish swirls.

One of the troopers had looked back to see the two of them.

Now he gestured to the Seeker.

"Ho, Modic."  They were not too far away for such a shout to carry, yet this greeting sounded as if it came from the other side of the sprawl of ruins, muddled and fuzzy.

"Ho, Modici" It was plain to Rentam that the Seeker was hesitating before, at last, he urged his sorry horse to amble on.  Had the man actually sent this motley crew of his ahead to be picked off by any hidden enemy, thus securing his own entrance?  Rentam saw him raise his hand as if to pull off the odorous hood but he did not complete that gesture.

Before they had yet reached the party there shot, from the heart of the ruins, a shaft of light, rippling color ... first the scarlet of man-blood, then the blue cast by the walls around.  It reached up to the heavens, as if to provide a guide to a whole army of men even if

they did not have the keen sight of the Betweeners.  Having shot heavenwards, it now twisted to the left, whirled just above the roofs of the still standing buildings, moving so fast that it wove a great wheel of light.  They might be standing again in full sun, save for the colors that touched them, first blue and then red and then blue again.

Having once established this circumference the haze descended again by sharp jerks until it engulfed the upper floors of the buildings and yet continued to descend.

Modic swung from his horse, grabbing hastily at his saddle bags and a coil of rope around the horn.  The horse had lost its early lethargy. It tossed its head as Modic left the reins hanging and retreated before the next circling of the light as might a man, step by step, keeping its head forward and up, while it whinnied and snorted and than gave a sharp cry such as Rentam had never heard issued from any mount before. Though he had not long to observe it, for Modic had caught his cloak-muffled arm in a grip which dug painfully into his flesh, and his light body was jerked by that hold into a pile of stone which was still connected to a standing wall on three sides.  Then Modic flung himself down, perforce taking the guide with him, so they lay flattened on a stony pavement.  The eye holes of the mask so shortened Rentam's vision that he could see nothing but a piece of wall, now red, now blue, and yet always bright at each viewing.

Perhaps he could not see, but hearing was not denied him.

Horses screamed.  There were other screams, too.  With the sounding of each of those he could feel the pressure of Modic's hand still lying heavy upon him keeping him down.  The Seeker was mouthing words in his own tongue in a steady litany.  Rentam recognized the name of one of the river land gods.  Was Modic striving to make magic in a place already so ridden by the threat of evil?  If so he was the greater fool, magic drew upon magic for feeding power, and somehow Rentam believed that Modic's spell speaking would only encourage that which was on guard here.

So the guide waited, as they lay together under an overhang of an ancient building which was like a cave, for that which would also seek them out.

There was no more screaming from the horses.  Once they heard a clatter of hooves showing that one of the mounts was less panicked, able to flee.  There was instead a whimpering which tore at Rentam's mind with the hurt and fear that it bore.  Even that was done in time and yet they lay still.  The colors no longer swept over the stone which was all Rentam could watch.  And humming, which he had not been really aware of until then, was gone.  It was quiet enough so that he could hear the two deep breaths... almost like sobs... which Modic uttered as he took away his prisioning hand.

Rentam edged as far as he could out of range of the Seeker's reach and sat up.  There was still light overhead, but that was drawing together into the single beam which had first sent it forth.

About them the full night was drawing in.

Modic raised up, not to his feet but instead crawled on hands and knees to an aperture through which he could see to where the men of his party had gathered.  There he squatted while Rentam leaned back against the wall, satisfying what had become a weakening hunger with a portion of journey rations he twisted off the tight cone of the stuff which he carried.  He had no desire to view what must have been a battlefield of sorts.  Now with his right hand he stroked the empty knife sheath at his belt.  If he were to come through this venture ... alive ... he would need a weapon of sorts.

Perhaps Modic was saving him for a secondary sacrifice ... Rentam squared his shoulders back against the wall.  The Seeker had now no followers, the guide was sure of that even though he had not looked beyond as Modic was doing.  Certainly he had no armament which could stand against a circle of killing light.  Modic was but a man without a following, no threat to Rentam's clan.  The guide's hand crept out of his cloak and he began to feel about him in the growing darkness.  One finger suddenly smarted and instantly he was feeling along something which had a knife's shape right enough, but lacked the smoothness of metal, even though it was edged, as more delicate touch suggested.  He still dared not look at what he had found, but continued to tug the object loose from where it had been planted almost straight up with only a finger's breadth or so of blade already uncovered.  Wriggling it with care Rentam kept his gaze on the Seeker, freeing the find by touch alone.

Modic, in this gloom, resembled a headless body for the bag mask covered his full head.  He was breathing noisily ... as might a man who had been running quite a distance.  Then he spoke, in a very low voice, which was so muffled by the bag, Rentam barely heard.

"The poor devils..."

Strange that he would mourn men he had sent to whatever frightening death the whirling colors had cloaked.  Rentam could never understand this man.  If one of his own kind made an enemy, and that was seldom, for their barren life was precious to the Betweeners, none worked out

such elaborate plot as this.  Instead either of the two took their quarrel to the Speaker.  There they talked, each telling what was in his mind and heart.  Sometime it did lead to a battle with the hands and there would be hurts to tend.  But death never entered in ... that was too familiar a visitor on its own to be deliberately summoned.

Now Modic had stripped himself of his main threat, the men who rode in this train.  There was certainly that between him and Rentam which sooner or later would lead to open confrontation.

The guide was not afraid but he accepted wariness to be a part of his thinking and planning from this time forth.  He had freed the thing in the earth.  Glancing up now and then to make sure that

Modic was paying no attention, he brought it forth, holding it under one of the flaps of his cloak to examine it more clearly.

It was, he believed, made of stone ... but not the same as that which formed the buildings moldering around them.  As long as his thin forearm it was a blade with a butt end surely intended for a hilt and a sharp point.  The tip of that had been broken off, but the remained

possessed a cutting edge.  This was a shimmer of color.

As the defense of the city had been red and blue interweaving, so this was a gray-white, in the depths of which showed gem beauty, red, golden, green, blue.  Those colors moved when one turned the blade from side to side.  Had Rentam seen this cut into gem size, he would have believed he had a fortune in his hand.  As it was he shoved it quickly back into full hiding.  Hoping to have escaped Modic's eyes he slipped the blade into an inner loop of his cloak.

However, as Rentam dropped his fingers from the hilt, he was still aware of a tingling, a prickling.  Modic had not moved.  He had thrust head and shoulders as far as he could through the spy hole he had chosen.  For a space there was quiet between them.  Rentam viewed the ruins about him, trying to guess what had been the original use of this now vanished building.  At the same time, with the patience of a Xole caught waiting to make a heo prey he began a new search with his long prehensile toes trying to discover if any more treasure lay beneath the scum of wind-driven sand.  His claws raked across the rock which appeared to be a flooring but each piece of that he so located was firm set and could not be lifted out.  If another one of these gem-bladed knives awaited discovery it would take more time and perhaps a lot of extra digging to uncover it.

As Modic moved Rentam ended such exploration.  The Seeker drew back from his hole and untied his bag mask, signaling Rentam to do likewise.

"There is naught to fear ... for now!"  Sweat had plastered his greasy hair flat to the skull, and small trickles of moisture made their way down, to drip from his square chin.

"You have been here before...."  Rentam spoke aloud the suspicion which had been growing in him ever since the Seeker had waved on his men and taken a slower pace.

"No!"  Modic sounded overly emphatic in that.

"No!"  His hand went to the breast of his thigh-length over robe where he had put the map stone for safe keeping.

"No ..."

Rentam's tongue flicked out from between his jaws and in again.  Once it was said that those of his blood could test the very air to sift truth from falsehood.  If that gift had been lost they had other small ways of dealing with any double talk from strangers.

Oddly enough Rentam had to believe that Modic was now speaking the truth.  Yet he was not ready to allow the Seeker to believe he had satisfied his unwilling companion by so much as that.  And perhaps there was a frayed feeling of right within the man which brought out of him an explanation Rentam was sure he had never meant to give.

Modic once more caressed his chin under the crust of sweat and plaster of sand, studying the guide narrowly.

"The Old Ones, those who lived here," he made a gesture indicating the ruins, "had many secrets.  Is not that the reason for both Seeker and Guide to come hither?"

Rentam shook his head.

"We wrest no secrets from the dead...."

"The more fools you."  Modic got to his feet, stretching arms and legs as if the time he spent at the spy hole had rendered him stiff.

"If you seek not for treasures, why do you venture into this sin-damned land year after year?  What brings you here?"

Rentam once more flicked his tongue over his lower lip taking the grit of sand into his mouth.  With it there seemed to come that sickening flavor with which the mask was imbued.  He plucked that off and shook head and shoulder much as the Seeker had stretched.

Then he deliberately wet a forefinger against his lips, used it to gather up some grains of sand from a nearby wall stone and licked that up.  A moment later he spewed it forth.

"Now what do you do?"  Modic wanted to know.

"There is salt in this earth...."  In turn Rentam got to his feet and looked about the jumble of wall and piles of fallen stone.

"Salt!"  Modic hooted with what he must consider laughter, still Rentam slowly surveyed each standing wall, seeking something which was not there.

"I asked you, Guide," the Seeker returned to the question, "what seek you within this desert if you come not to plunder the towns?  Do the demons walk only in those so you feel safe in the open ... ?"

Rentam's two strides took him even with and then past Modic.

Now he needs must kneel to look upon what had so engrossed the Seeker.

"We seek," his voice was absent in tone, for what he told was not secret... neither was it ever believed, "water."

"Water!"  Modic's voice arose to a whoop.

"Here in the dead sands you seek water?  Be like you follow some old tale where some ancient evil one struck stone and it enclosed your precious water."

Rentam did not turn his head, he found that he must crouch even lower to look through Modic's vantage point.

"You have the truth of it, Seeker," he answered still absently.  Then even forgot the man by his side when he looked out to where the horse and men had waited.  Sun was gone, shadows were heavy.  In his nostrils was the raw, sweet smell of blood, and he saw enough to near bring the scanty contents of his stomach up into his mouth.  Bones... goblets of torn flesh.  But the bones were the worst, for from the way they lay twisted and piled against each other he could believe that something might have stripped their bodies of flesh while yet they lived.  There was a head which had rolled closer to his viewpoint and was exposing bone to chin and cheek and a mass tattered of flesh above.  Yet by Hyqur, the Keeper of the Gates of Darkness, the flesh had not been devoured or even carried far.  The still dripping chunks and strips lay within what once must have been a fountain, pulled into a pile as if laid out for a feast.

Modic's hand fell heavily on his shoulder.

"Quiet as the sand when there is no puff of air to give it life."  He was crouched beside Rentam again, his mouth so close to the Betweener's leathery cheek that the foulness of his breath for an instant made Rentam gag as he had from the mask.

"There are those who come to feast at such a table...."

"Yet," Rentam dropped his own voice and half hissed, half whispered, "you have not been here before.  Then how do you know what chances here? Let me guess, Seeker.  You had full knowledge of that which killed and took precautions that you should not be among the slain by coming last.  Why chose you ..."

His question was interrupted by a soft sound like a heavy sigh such as a beast of burden might give when loosed of that burden, the need for going on.  The darkness was not quite as complete as it would have been outside the ruins.  Rentam was not sure just where the pale light came from, unless it was from the uncovered bones of the city itself.  But he was able to see the outline of a horse's head against whitish block a little beyond them.

Modic chuckled.  He might not have been viewing a fatal battlefield, but rather was anticipating some coming gift.

"So ... SOOOO ... sssoooo ... Dus," again that whispering voice but he did not address Rentam this time.  The mount's ugly head swung in his direction and the horse took one step and then another as one answering a detested jerk upon dangling reins, edging by as far as it could from the horror about the pool.

"Never judge a mount by looks."  Modic dug an elbow into Rentam's ribs.

"Dus has been a-questing before.  But he has been thrice blessed by the Voice of Ugan and also endowed at birth with more brains than many a man!  Ugly and spare he may look, but he is as fresh at the trail's ends as when he first stepped out.  Ah!"

Modic's first touch on the guide's arm became a grasp which twisted flesh and brought pain.

"Look you, Betweener!  Here comes those to the banquet their protector has laid out for them!"

The horse had managed to reach their crowded hide just as his master spoke.  The animal made no sound but his sweat was that of fear and it was rank in their small space.  Giving voice to a harsh whinny Dus turned and pulled away.  Modic did not appear to notice his going. Rentam saw a dark shape detach itself from a fraction of wall to scuttle towards the basin of blood and flesh.  It was only the first. However Rentam was not to be turned by such a sight from his need for the truth.

"You know this place."  He made a statement out of that, not a question.

"Yet you swear you have never been here before."

"Nor have I, Betweener.  But I have been to Lyrh and Kenzy...."  He spoke with pride in his voice.

"Though never within these walls.  Yet I saw a Seeker disappear into Lyrh with all his company.  And he did not return, nor did any one or thing, save my fool Dus here, when the sun arose the next morning. There were sounds in a plenty during the night and they were not pleasant ones.

"If you were so near, how does it that you were not caught in the same trap?"

Again Modic chuckled.  " Twas my own thinking which saved me there.  I was well behind the Seeker, not a member of his crew, and when the killing light came I was beyond its radius.  Also ..."

His hand strayed inside his robe again and Rentam would swear that what he sought was that map.... "Also, I sat at the feet of many story tellers... in all the Down Lands.  Some had one small bit to spew forth, some had nothing ... but I listened with patience for more than a year.  I even had such brought to tell to me alone.

It was one of those, an ancient Speaker of your own kind, Betweener, who gave me the first clue."  He settled back into the shadows and sat more at ease with his back against a broken wall.  Yet he still spoke in so low a tone that Rentam had trouble making sure of all the words.

"What do you know of the tale of Lonscraft, Betweener?  Or is that legend so' old it has dried up in all men's minds, to be blown away in an autumn tempest?"

Truth?  Rentam's tongue tasted the air.  There were many foul and dangerous odors about but he could still pick up this Seeker.

Modic told the truth, or what he believed to be the truth, or... at least a portion of it, destined to hook Rentam to him.

"Lonscraft."  He remembered back to days not so long ago when he had toiled over learning... names, places, events which had been the portion of the Betweeners lore for such a long time.

"Lonscraft," he repeated, "is a tale...."

"What are the past doings of us all but legends when time speeds further and further away from the event," Modic wanted to know.

"Yes, there is the tale of Lonscraft... but it is worn ragged by passing through so many tellers, each changing a little to make it suit his or her own ideas of what was exciting, or fitting, or proper.

Your people tell dark stories of the cities within this dead land, yet they learn its trails and mark its guide posts as if such acts are a matter of unchangeable law.  You do believe yet, deep inside of you, there is a faint stirring when one calls the name of a vanished city.

You have built up a number of taboos and most of them have truth in them.  Your training tells you that death was here ... and it was. Still you are not aware of what kind of death ... only of its shadow. But me, Modic," he thumped himself on the chest, "I allow no story to stand alone and be only half believed.  Always have I sought for more. I heard of the woman Kasiu, she who was first wife to Amers.  Her I hunted out and she was afraid, for there were many in her village who knew how much she hated her husband and who were skeptical of her story of Demons entering him when he came here.  I made a bargain with her, that she could travel with my company down to the River towns and that she was grateful for, also she could not guess that more lay in her husband's journey bag upon his return than crumbs of food.  But I learned where she had spilled the bag, so I found what I sought for what seems now half my life.

"There was the map and I hardly think truly that it was of his own making ... it may be generations old.  Also there were some guide scratches... look for yourself, Betweener."

Modic was holding out an oblong of slate painstakingly ground into a narrow slip.  Rentam accepted it gingerly, then might have gasped had his species been that of the Seeker.  It was hot in his hand, not as something which had gathered body warmth from resting against flesh, but with a heat which radiated from it.  He could have been holding an actual part of the sun's beam.  To the sight in this part-dark it was bare, but when his fingers quested over it, ridges and curves lay plain against his skin.  Deep in him was that first flutter of fear known when a thing which is thought to be without truth suddenly throws aside the cloak of falsehood.  His lips shaped words which his voice whispered:

"In the ninth month when the Lords of the Three Lands strove together, there came out of the depths of the dead and riven land one who was veiled and lacking in speech.  Yet no one raised hand to pull aside the veil and cloak, or spoke.  Rather did they draw back away from this one who was not like unto others of the world.

"Then rose up Utyr of Lonscraft who was ever of hasty tongue and impatient hand.  He spoke, saying that truth was to be known and if there was a message then let this one speak it forthwith.

"So that one from the dead land turned to Utyr and made certain gestures which no one understood, but which had an ill look to them. Utyr, though he shifted from one foot to the other as a person ill at ease, did not speak again.  Nor did he give any orders to his men as

that shrouded one turned and walked from him.  Those before the walker hunched to either side making a free path for the cloaked one.  Thus the stranger came to the first opening of the broad marsh which was then to the gates of Lonscraft, that city being partly built on landing of stone long and deep set in unsteady earth.  Going out upon one of the piers of the swift flying marsh boats, the stranger opened wide his cloak, which then hung in the air itself like wings.  Although all the company stayed ashore and none could see what the cloak had hidden.

"But a hand flashed forth bearing such a weapon as no man had seen ... white, and gold, blue, red and green, color followed color across its surface.  Then the stranger whistled, a clear, sharp sound like the cry of some sea bird.

"Down one of the aisles of open water which served for the boats came that which those of the land had never seen.  It was both a fish and a crawler upon the land for it showed stubbly legs.

When it came to a belt of weed it climbed over that growth, not giving way to it.

"As for the staff, this flashed with color, mainly green, but also swirling red, blue, and gold.

"The head of the water one was held high above the surface, and from its mouth issued words which all man could hear but none could answer, for there was no understanding them.  Then the voice grew louder, boomed and belled, until it filled the ears of all those in Lonscraft and there was no escaping it.  Also it carried in it, even if one could not understand the words, a feeling of coming shadow and ill fortune. So that those waiting by Utyr drew sword or battle knife, even though no challenge had been offered.

"Utyr himself strode forward near enough to the stranger that he might grasp that one's shoulder if he wished; he even put forth his hand as if to do that very thing.  Yet he did not complete that gesture for the thing in the water ceased upon an instant its calling and there was a strange and abiding silence which held for five breaths, perhaps more. Then he who stood at the pier's end turned slowly around so that those gathered there could see, that though he walked upright and cloaked as might a man of the city, he was not of their form nor wore any covering known to them...."

"Yes," Modic broke in, "do your tellers of ancient tales say then what manner of creature this stranger was?"

Rentam's tongue flicked out, he raised the water carrier to his wide mouth and took the smallest of sips, though that was enough to strengthen his voice.

"You have heard the same tale, Seeker..  . what manner of creature was this stranger?"  prodded Modic.

Then he laughed.  There was a shadow of contempt in his voice:

"Go hunt out a quiet pool and look into it, Guide.  There shall you see well what you wear... for the stranger was of your kin by blood."

What Rentam might have replied to that was lost, for from the broken walls before them arose a keening cry, and straightway that was stifled in turn by cries and shouts of despair, horror and terror on the verge of madness.  If some had escaped the massacre in the open they were now being dragged to their deaths.

So awesome was that chorus that Rentam put his hands over his ears but found he could not shut out the sound which seemed to enter and pulsate in his body so he rocked a little forward and back as if he was shaken by something a great deal stronger than any sound, no matter how hideous.

A musky-sweet corruption of blood scent arose about him also.

Thus he could believe that those scavengers of this ill-omened place gathered again for a feasting.  There was movement behind him and he whirled to see something which slid through the black of shadow to advance past the end of a broken wall.  From that spread the odor of

horse sweat, Dus once more.  The fear born in animal broke through the ugly spell which kept both travelers quiet.  Modic did not move, but Rentam stepped forward and caught again that trail of broken rein.  By this he drew the bony horse to them.

Behind he heard once again Modic's chuckle as eerie as a madman's.

"Did I not say," Modic asked, "that Dus was one of the best of all that train?  The rest stood pinned by fear until they met death, but this one fled, which is often the greater part of any valor, and note its coming does us also a service.  For it would not venture to us now again if the way was not clear.  Now yield your guide ship to me, Betweener, and we shall come out of this... but tell me first what sorcery your distant kin worked here which defeated Utyr, and with him many other lords of a land not then dead."

"That the tellers of tales never knew," Rentam returned sharply.

The moans, screams, and cries of fear and torment had died away as if one by one those who voiced them were being silenced forever.

"And the water thing which came to his call?  What was that, Betweener? Why during one day and night did all those who followed Utyr die? What death twisted and wrung their bodies, tore and shredded the very flesh which made them what they were?"

Modic advanced a step or two, now facing Rentam.  There was a full moon and, as if he still clung to some ancient fear for all his brave talk, he was fingering the broken rein and standing close enough to the horse that he might be in the saddle and off before Rentam could move.

The Betweener shrugged.

"I know nothing of sorcelment or the plays of warlocks and Mages."

"Ha!  And still those of the stranger's kin went out of the city untouched.  None of them bore so much as a water bottle with them, bareheaded they went, un pursued and free.  That is the ending of the tale they chant in the Down Lands.  Eh, Guide, how fared them?  Death did not claim them."

"I know no such ending of the legend," countered Rentam.

"When it is spoken among us death is universal."

Modic grinned evilly.

"Do men, or Betweeners, ever really make that clear?  Perhaps it is better to forget than to admit one has made some pact with that which should never have been thought of?  Do we greet Betweeners with open arms and fair smiles to this day ... even when they bring us those things we have need of?  Why come you in parties of fighters if you are merchants with nothing to fear?"

Rentam gestured with one hand as if brushing aside something worn threadbare, an action with its reason lost far back in time.

"Why do we stand here," he asked, "and talk of old tales and whether or not there was death of a city, a curse which grew out of Utyr's orders when he went desert raiding.  Rather it would be well for us now to be on our way before that guardian returns, to jealously remove us from its present lair."

"True, true.  We shall go hence from here."  Modic looked about him as if he stood in some noisome place.

"But from Lonscraft we go not until..."  He brought out of the bosom of his robe something which fitted into the hollow of his hand and which he handled as carefully as if he held a palm full of water which he must carry without its draining away.

"Give me the map...."

Rentam handed him that oblong of stone which had the message on it near erased.  With this firmly held in his left hand, Modic clapped his right hand about also.  Though it looked to be a shard of dull gray, such as lay in the thousands along any trail, Modic was touching it to the map.

It was if he now held a coal, for there sprang up a steady red light in the stone.  Modic's features twisted, his lips grimaced as if he did indeed carry a fire's heat against flesh.  The fire was answered by a spark on the map, one which glowed as steadily as the Seeker's stone. Modic gave a half-stifled oath, his eyes wide and brightly open so that he would not lose a fraction of what he looked upon.

With the wane of the moon Modic stepped as forward boldly as he would have had it been day.  For the lack of anything on which to base a protest, Rentam followed after, leading the horse which plodded as if it had been sentenced to too heavy a 'task.

Lonscraft.  In Rentam's mind revolved the name of that ancient death of a city.  So far the tale he himself had repeated had been exact..  . yet never had it told what manner of death was spewed forth by the marshes, or why it had not fallen upon those of Betweener blood, just those of Modic's species.

Still, in the many years since that time, perhaps too many to be told over without a knot string to aid, those who ventured into the Great Dry had died... one way or another.  None had told what they had chanced upon which was so perilous an enemy.

Lonscraft itself was the name which had been gasped by one of the earlier venturers as he died, tongue stricken save for that word.

They now angled well away from the open center about the dead pool where the others had died.  The memory of the color which arose to slay, or else hold the intruders here until something more subtle had come seeking life and blood, haunted Rentam.  His hand beneath his cloak sought out that piece of fire curling stone which he had found in the ruin.  Yes, there was a brilliant swatch of color to match that which had flashed to kill on the rod or knife.

With each step he took, he glanced sharply about and then at the blade. The star-dotted sky above the central buildings remained free of lighting or change.  Though color still swirled within the pointless blade, it did not even reflect on the hand which held it.  Still there was a feeling..  . Rentam's head jerked as if that sudden thought had been a blow.  Why did he come to imagine thus as he followed Modic through these ruins?  Never before had he conceived of things which were not of the earth he knew.

Oh, there had been tales a-plenty concerning demons and creatures from other worlds (with hints that the meddling of some man or Betweener had opened forgotten gates), but always such had appeared or had happened to some guide or wanderer from another clan.  One far away enough for the report to become muddled and overlaid with all the fears which were a part of their heritage.

He knew well that the men of the lower lands by the rivers had similar ghosts.  Nor were there many who even dared to make a short essay into the Dry with or without a guide.  Still there was about Modic now a kind of fever which darkened his skin even under the moon's glow, and made his journey one of erratic pauses and swifter advances, as if two desires warred violently within him, now this and now that taking command.

It was the horse who broke through the Seeker's tight absorption.

Not uttering any sound, it drew back upon the rein, jerking its head as if to free itself.  Bracing its spindly legs within a narrow way between two piles of rubble, it refused to advance.

Modic at once appeared fully awakened from his obsession.  He stood dragging with all his force at the reins... the horse's head now stretched forward at a painful angle.  It was the animal that struck first.  It kicked out, though it was not facing Modic, and Rentam , who had had no part in its pull forward, was the victim of that assault.

There was a keening wail... not from either man or beast in their struggle, nor from Rentam either.  The guide threw himself backward, not only to escape the hooves of the animal but in utter surprise .. . for the sound issued from the artifact he had found.  Nor did it emit a single note, rather a near scream which was suddenly cut off.  Neither the horse nor Modic turned to see what had made that cry.  Rather the horse sprung forward, near overrunning the man as it burst out of the narrow way between the two tottering pillars of rubble.

The light from the moon was gone.  Clouds built up in the northern sky. Rentam's instinct told him a storm was on the way.

But that was of little importance when compared to this thing he had found.  It was emitting a droning beat, broken now and then as if each portion of sound was a word of warning or a threat.

He could have turned in the moment and found his way out of this dead curl of broken walls and mounds of stone.  The horse and Modic had vanished around a turn in the debris so that he could not be seen.

It was not curiosity, nor any sense of responsibility toward Modic, which brought him apart from the way where he had taken refuge some moments earlier.  Seemingly of its own accord the hand holding the weapon (if weapon it was) shook free from his cloak without his willing it.  The colors within were running as if he were turning the stone about in his hand.  It was .. .

For a second, perhaps even less, he opened his eyes to their greatest extent.  The thing was moving weapon-wise at last, though there was no enemy before him.  His muscles responded as they never had to any journey knife or battle staff, thrusting and recovering with a knowledge which he knew he had never learned in any clan drill.  His hand and arm might now be possessed by ... By the dead?  In all the lore taught by his people there was no room for such an idea.  One was born, lived, and when the time set had come, one died.  Nor had the ken any tales of the walking of the dead, troubling from those who were past all of this world's sorrows, acts, thoughts.  The dead spoke not... between them and the living there was not even the thinnest crack of a doorway.

It was not the dead suspicioned so to frighten some of the Seeker's people and be a part of the dangers of the Dry as far as they were concerned.  The Betweeners hinted of dealing with dark powers.  Demons . . . some of his kin, he knew, believed that there were unseen malignant forces at loose in ancient cities.  This city . . .

Rentam stopped short and stared unseeingly at the shard he held.  What of that story Modic had asked of him, a story long current among his own people?  The cloaked one from out of the desert who had gone to the marsh pier and thereafter summoned a thing past any man's knowing.

Rentam, still keeping the broken sliver in his hand under a flap of clothing, strode in the direction Modic and his mount had taken. Rounding a tall heap of debris he came abruptly into the open once more.  There was just enough light to see a square ahead and the facades of the buildings forming its sides had apparently suffered less from whatever doom had erased Lonscraft.  Directly across from him was a seemingly intact building which bore no signs of ruin at all.  The wide doorway was above the level of the square so that a flight of broad steps led to its open doorway.  Strangest of all in this desert country, there was a runnel which had cut its way through the steps, to a hole which gaped at ground level.  Running water?  No, the color was wrong.  Each drop of that small flood was as scarlet as newly shed blood.  While above its surface, back and forth, danced winged things which skimmed so closely to the small flood that they might have been swallowed up, yet always they coasted to safety beyond.

Modic had lost hold on the broken rein, the horse backed away ffrom the steps and the liquid on them, showing the whites of its eyes, foam dripping from its nostrils to slime its nose and the bony expanse of its chest.  It retreated from Modic, from the building.

Then it swung half around and cantered awkwardly to Rentam's left. Modic was pulling on the head-concealing mask that he had worn when they had entered Lonscraft.  As he did so he walked as does one who bends his body against the force of a mountain wind, taking one slow step and then another.  He gestured force ably with one arm as if to keep off an attack of flies.  While in his other hand was that map which now was a fire to light the whole of the stairway.

If that spark of light upon it had been fashioned to beckon, now surely it proclaimed to be nearly to the goal.

The smooth running rill was disturbed on the surface, now dimpled as if a shower fell upon it.  The flies gathered in the upper air to become a black blot, still over the water but hovering above Modic as he climbed.

Rentam shivered.  He had known fear before, but it had always been caused by things he understood ... of one of the Vort beasts raiding the herds of the Betweeners... of the sickness which was supposed to strike anyone invading the old cities, of the ill will of his own clan should he break their few but skintight taboos (for that would un clan him and make him as one dead walking among the living).  Now... this was like fronting a cold rage, an are so great that his kin could not even sense more than a portion of it.

Here lay in wait a will, a power, a brutal rule which shook him.

Still the time had come ... or he had come ... too far past the borders of its control to struggle against it now.

A will, a power ... he was caught up by sharp command as he came fully into the open passing the horse that now stood with drooping head as if the beast had lost all hope.  This horse lived, so did Modic as he climbed from one step of the wide stair to the next.  Still, though

Rentam began search with his own heightened guide's sense, he could trace back that bold assault against him to nothing!  There was no trace of man, of Betweener, of animal, of life as he knew it, aroused to draw him shivering towards the source.  To that highly developed sense, trained to locate life, there came, at last, an answer from a source he had not expected.

From the broken tip of the many-colored blade sped a thin thread of red and blue, entwined one with the other.  Those were the same colors as the light which had been thrown across the rubble-lined streets of Lonscraft... the fearsome alien weapon.

What did Rentam now hold?  An artifact which was a dueling ground for bursts of killing color?  By arousing his will, pitting his inner strength against that pull, the guide was able to linger on the second step, even as Modic reeled and wavered far closer to that aperture above which served as an ever open door.

Inch by inch Rentam edged around to look back over the way he had come. The horse screamed and reared to strike out with its front feet as might a war-trained stallion.  Around it ringed a crowd of shadows, curious moving bolts of darkness which never clearly showed themselves. Though there were a number of these remains gathered around the horse, others padded to the foot of the stair to form a double line of dark forms, though they avoided the running rill.  Rentam flicked out his tongue in their direction.  Full of viciousness, yes, but these were not a true part of that which waited within.  However they now formed a guard wall against any retreat, and that could only mean that Modic and he were being edged towards another and doubtless more powerful enemy.

His foot touched on the next step.  There was a crackling, the sound of something rolling back toward the waiting band.  Rentam saw a skull, polished enough to reflect the gleam of this alien light.

He no longer watched the hunters, rather studied his footing.  That remnant of his own species, or Modic's, was not alone.  There lay a scattering of broken bones, some near reduced to powder, along each step.

He heard a thin, half-muffled cry which might have come from Modic, muffled as he was by mask.  The Seeker tripped, fell to his knees on the last step, his shoulders shaking, his head turning from side to side as if so he tried to avoid blows.  Some strong compulsion drew him on to crawl along the platform above as might a seriously injured animal seeking shelter.  There was no cracking of splintering bones now, all sound had been absorbed by a deep hum which hurt Rentam's ears, throbbed through his body.  Two more strides brought the guide

beside Modic.  He reached down and hooked his fingers in the other's armpit, giving a steady pull, while the Seeker scrambled in the bones and flopped about, seeming unable regain to his feet.

"Up!"  He was so near to Modic Rentam believed that his words were not lost in that ever growing throb.

"Up to your feet, Seeker.

Would you meet battle on your knees, already so far spent as you seem?"

Modic turned his shaking head to look up at Rentam dull eyed.

Spittle ran from the corner of his mouth and with it a thread of blood from a lip he had bitten though.  He showed no understanding, but some part of the guide's urgency must have reached him, as he swung around to clasp both of his sweat slicked hands on Rentam's arm.  Using that hold for leverage as he might a tree or rock pillar, he drew himself up, near over setting Rentam in the process, when for a moment or two he hung a dead weight on the other before regaining his feet.

The throbbing grew heavier, more assertive as if something ahead was impatient at their delay.  As they moved forward, Modic, still using Rentam as a support, they were plunged into light... a blaze of blue.  Modic halted, stopping Rentam almost in midstride, to jerk at the edge of the mask the guide had worn into the city.

"Put on," he croaked hoarsely, his mouth close to the guide's nearest ear.

One-handed, for he could not put aside the gem light he held, the Betweener obediently pulled on the mask once again though he did not like the curtailment of sight which wearing it caused.

Only it was true that once he was again shrouded that blaze of raw light was subdued, and he could see enough to mark the fact they they were indeed in a palace or some incredibly rich shrine.

The light might blot out a measure of response from the display of unbelievable wealth about them, but it could not utterly hide what was set in patterns on the walls, and not only on the walls.  There were dunes and drifts of precious metals and gem stones across the floor, many of the pieces broken.

As they shuffled on they tramped on a medley of stones and metals of stones and metals such as could not be seen at a fair even if all which had ever changed hands there had been reassembled for one great showing.

There were weapons, too, swords and knives possessing hilts rich in jewels, strange other objects which were certainly not intended for adornment but which, if weapons, Rentam did not recognize.

Here and there was a rack of bones .. . some draped with chains of office of the adornment of chief wives.  Several of these lay broken across the things which Rentam believed might be weapons.

Before them was still that blast of light which gave no hint of its source or purpose .. . unless that latter was death, which Rentam could well believe.  In his hands the colored spindle of stone quivered past all his endeavors to control it, but so far it had not broken free.

His tongue touched the rough stuff of the mask, the tip of it pointed through the hole which served for the mouth cutting and the opening for breathing.  Deliberately he began to try to set the pace for himself, to be quickly forced into the maelstrom of color.

It was a battle, and his uncovered skin pricked and stung.  Modic had again fallen to hands and knees.  Even his head hung low so he did not watch the way ahead, he merely crawled toward the source of the light.

Rentam was able to slow his advance though he could not tear himself free of the strong pull upon him.  Still he quested with tongue tip, thrusting that even farther into the crackling air about.

The light must have a source, and having a source it must be set, meant to protect it's own inner sanctum as he had seen its overflow light up the sky in the first coming of their party.  Animal, biped, brain . . . thought process which?

His flesh was so seared by assault... what awaited him?  For the first time ... his Betweener-born organ for detection brought him no knowledge.  There was nothing ahead, that sense insisted, but the light itself, and that was not tended by any living thing.

The way was growing narrower as the great room started to close in about them to form a corridor.  Here the treasure was less visible. There were more skeletons, insignias of office mingled with brittle bones, and there were indeed weapons he knew, some lying half into the red flood of the stream from which he edged away as it began to flow widening more and more.  The stench rising from it was choking.  Rentam coughed hollowly and leaned with one hand against the wall as he steadied himself against unseen gusts which struck him.

Modic halted.  Then he hunched in a crouch, sweeping his hands from side to side about him though without seeming to see what lay there. By chance his fingers curved about one of the rodlike things which Rentam believed was a weapon.  Still not raising his head so that he might look at what he had found, the Seeker allowed the rod to slip through his fingers until a dark band meant for a grip was resting in his hold.

Rentam was not prepared for what followed.  Modic swung around, moving with the speed of a trained hand and foot warrior.

The end of that rod pointed unerringly at Rentam's middle, though the Seeker still did not lift his head.

No!  Rentam's sense had never proved to be deceptive but it had to be so now ... it had to be!  There was life in the other but it had dwindled down as might the last coal of a fire being fast smothered. In its place ... the guide's tongue tip sent a thrill of pain through his body, kept him pinned to the wall.  There was life ending ... and nothing, nothing gathered beyond to take its place.

Yet Modic was on his knees, his head hanging forward nearly resting on his chest.

Not dead ... possessed!  Other evil tales from the wild slipped into memory.  The Seeker gave body room and aid to something else.... Only, when Rentam strove to touch that, to discover what had chained the River worlder to such a trap, he could not pick up anything save always the burning of the power.

Rentam jerked his body to the left as that weapon pointed in his direction.  He felt the heat of a ray which burst at him.  It was gone as quickly as two breaths, though Modic still held it aimed at the Betweener.  Rentam saw the other's hand tighten about the band on the rod with full strength.

The shining length of his own find was ready.  In its heart, flaring from the butt to the broken point, was a rich roll of color.

That twisted as if to wrench itself free but Rentam's six fingers held tight.  His whole body jerked as if the artifact from the city ruin was a rope with him imprisoned in a loop.  He flailed out with his other arm, striving to keep his balance, and so struck against Modic.

Whether the unexpected contact between their bodies was the reason or not, the Seeker staggered halfway around to bring up the strange weapon.  That gesture was never completed, for Modic's rod, touching by chance the broken knife Rentam unconciously advanced in defense, burst, scattering fragments which melted to drip to the floor.  Spots of dull dark blue fell smoking and glowing at their cores.  The Seeker lurched forward, his unsteady pace close to a run, shouldering Rentam aside. The guide went after him at a speed which was nearly equal.

They came upon more skeletons.  However the bones were scattered, no rack of them whole.  Also they appeared as if they were more recent than those in the hallway.  Another Seeker band which had reached this point before falling prey to an enemy they could not sense?  Rentam

wondered.

In the center of the large chamber beyond was a bank of chairs, constructed, not of stone, but of some substance which glittered with dancing lights.  Before those bubbled a pool from which arose the dread runnel of red they had companied with from without.  It appeared to Rentam that small bursts of flame danced over surface just as had the black insects in the outer world.

At the entrance of the pool crouched something which was surely out of some nightmare of the damned.  Rentam, gazing at it with horror was near overborne.  For it might be that one of his kin, larger, mad with blood lust, stared straight into his eyes as if the mask he still wore

was transparent.  The thing's mouth gaped wide and the pointed fangs within dripped glowing slime into the pool.

It was not dead.  His own guide's sense told him rather it had never lived as he knew life.  There was nothing at all Rentam could detect from it.  While in the seats... Yes, there sat dead ... six bodies, not riven and torn, not reduced to racks of bones..  ..

These were not Betweeners, nor Seekers, nor of any race Rentam had knowledge of.  What he could see of their skin (they wore wrappings which covered most of it) was a dark blue.  The hands of each were spread out so the withered fingers could lie upon a series of buttons upon lap boards which perhaps kept each in his chair.

From this scene, the pool, and the long dead, there thrust upward a beam of light.  Even as Rentam sighted it that beam pulsed again and again and then vanished.  He drew in breath and expelled it again in a hiss which near carried away his mask.  The hands of the dead had moved

. . . pressing certain of those buttons.

While the thing in the pool dropped its scaled muzzle into the slimy flood and drank--or seemed to do so.  Yet that was impossible, Rentam's senses still told him there was no life here.  If there had ever been it was long since gone.

Modic scrambled along the edge of the pool.  His head no longer hung down but his features were twisted in such an expression of rage as Rentam had never seen.

The Seeker's mouth worked as he threw his mask into the pool, his eyes never leaving Rentam's face.  Now he half turned and sprang forward to the nearest of those seats.  His hands closed upon the body there and he jerked it out of its perch to the floor, catching and holding the board as the body fell.  Now he seated himself where the corpse had been ... his fingers also spanning the board of buttons.

His whole body shook as he flung up his head and brayed wild laughter, his attention on the thing which had drunk and again raised its head to stare at Rentam.

"The hour is now!"  Modic's voice seemed to fill the place.  He might have been shouting with the full power of his lungs.

"Let that which purifies go forth and..."  His finger tips played a fluttering game on the board.

"This is the hour," he repeated.

"Broken was the pattern when these died."  He glanced at his dead companions.

"Some of their training lives on as was meant.  They rule the world...."  He leaned forward a little, spittle flicks on his lips, and yet he grinned and the wild exultation was not gone from his eyes....He nodded toward that thing on opposite bank of the pool.

"How go things with you, oh, Farguel?  Yes, you are dead and gone but the treasure you gave us still does its duty.  See this one of your kin ... he knows not even now what he has found ... the root of that which had made a desert of blooming land.  Dead!"  He pounded his hand on the

arm of the chair in which he sat.

"We died too soon!"  Again his face twisted in that horrifying way, as much of a mask as the one he had flung from him.

"We will it not!"  He pulled at his under robe as if it had begun to choke him.

"Dead, we shall take with us a dead world.  Come, brothern from the outer stars.  We shall move even as we have planned, for that one," he looked to Rentam, "shall be food for Farguel.  So fed life will return ... is that not so?  Have not I, Thebar, returned in the body of this

rover ... little by little he became me ... first as a whisper of treasure, and, when he had taken that, a stronger vision and a stronger.  Until he saw himself a conqueror and a king!

And he had heard of this guide who knew the desert so well and would provide him with the means of coming.... Ah, brothern, rejoice that I was strong, that though I was what men called dead, I was not, only abiding deep within another body waiting.

"Did I not grow the stronger even as the chosen one began to come nearer?  Did I not bid him send those fool beasts who followed him ahead that they might be harvested?  Yes, the doing was mine ... and now I shall be even as he who once wore this body ... Lord of the world ... a world!"

Again he screeched with laughter, and now he beckoned to Rentam "Come here, Betweener... look at Farguel who is what our voice called from the swamp!"  He gestured to the thing which drank.

"Once all you and your kin were as he.  That day shall come again.  For it is my will and desire, and only what I wish shall ever more happen here.  Look you ... and die!"

Rentam had seen men before who came raving from the wasteland.

This talk of bodies and of kingdoms yet to come ... those were only the dreams of a broken-headed man.  Yet when he watched the sureness of Modic's fingers on the board he had taken from the dead there was something in the man as well as in this place which no Betweener had

ever mentioned, which no legend enshrined from other years.  Who were those from the past who Modic called upon?  And this thing which had now lifted its head again from the deep red flood and stood, its jaws dripping red?  The thing which had no life, or never had had, but which moved even as he watched, teetering a little with its forepaws near into the flood.

Farguel, Modic had named it.  There was no such name in Betweener clans nor did any of his kin walk upon all fours.  That huge head swung a little toward him, the mouth gaped as if the thing could wish him to it for feasting.

But there was something wrong with that mouth!  Great fore fangs promised death ... in the strange light they changed in color with waves of blue, green, yellow, red running up and down.  Yes, he could see now ... one of these was missing.  Without conscious thought Rentam swung up the broken knife he had brought out of the ruins, comparing that to the dread fangs which the creature wore.  It was certainly the truth ... what he had must be a fang ... but from what jaw had it been taken?  This beast?  Surely it depended too much on luck for that to be the truth and Rentam's kind were suspicious of such a thing as luck.

"SSaaa .. ."  The sound was a hissing mighty enough to be from the throat of a king serpent himself, another traveler's tale the core of which perhaps to be found here.  Rentam blinked and blinked again.

That thing was changing form before his eyes.  In the desert wind devils could raise whole phantom cities to delude a traveler.

Yet never had they called her a Betweener.  Guides were immune to that troubling of sight.

The legs of the thing were being drawn back into its bloated body.  It now rested its belly flat.

"No!"  Where Modic had sat voicing insane laughter, he now arose in the chair, clasping the board before him, his fingers thudding home with force on the buttons.

"Farguel!"  he screamed at the hunched shape of that thing.

"Farguel, down with you to the battle even as we set together in thoughts of what must be done.

Was it not I, Thebar, who drew you from the swamp to this city, who delivered to you those who were as the beasts, only food to nourish you?  Remember, once you fought before and there were those who did not run and scream and strive to hide against that which allowed no hiding. Farguel, this two-legged meat standing here is such a one as those who drove you back, who starved you of food and drink, who made you what you are ... for I think, Farguel, you are no longer the death hunter you were when we sealed our bargain.  Kill this one, Farguel, and prove that you are again great and awesome, so that those sent to bear you down shall themselves die between your fangs.  Kill, Farguel!"

Surely this thing, for all its alteration of shape, was not alive as he sensed life!  Rentam watched it coil its serpent shape and lift high that head now losing all resemblance to his own.  It opened wide its mouth and a broken line of fangs was fully bared.  Not alive, not alive... Rentam held to that thought with all his strength of will.

Yet he could not judge whether it would answer Modic's order or not. His right hand still held in sight the fang, while the fingers of the other moved, writing on the air an unseen pattern.  He had believed that such learning was a legend mumbled over by the old ones of the clans, and when he had been set to learning all that finger play he had done so believing it was only a part of his training.

The great head halted in its reach across the flood.  Rentam felt a blow on his shoulder hard enough to numb his arm and near send him sprawling forward into the stream.  Modic's board of control lay but inches away on the very lip of the pool.

"Farguel, strike ... there is no way he can ..."

Modic was out of the seat, had sunk to his knees as he still held one arm over the chair and was manifestly trying to draw himself up again.

Rentam watched the creature closely.  Its head stretched even higher, supported by a long neck.  The open mouth displayed the loss of a front fang.

"Farguel..."  Modic's voice was harsh but faint as if that of the dead. Rentam fell back a step as he sensed what was happening to the Seeker. Life was receding.  No, now, returned again in a wave with a desperate surge.  Was Modic making a supreme effort against another force?  "SSaaa..."  hissing from the beast.  Then a singsong of words from Modic.  Only those words were not in any language that the guide could understand, drilled though as he was in the three major languages and numerous dialects of Between and River lands.  There was an authority in that chant.  Instinctively Rentam reached for the knife he did not wear.  The Seeker huddled again in the chair, his features strangely bloated as if he put on another type of mask.

Whatever he said was addressed, not to Rentam, but to the thing by the stream.  Modic raised his hands jerkily and outspread them again as if the button board still rested on his knees.  Then, seeming to understand dimly that that was gone, he voiced a wailing cry, such a sound as Rentam had never heard before, but the peril of which he could taste with his flickering tongue.

Modic did not face the guide but, at that moment, Rentam's body throbbed as if that sound reached within him to the very bones, took command of him, flesh and blood.  The head of the creature begun to swing again.  Rentam, in spite of his struggle to command himself, moved toward the lip of the pool.  Also ... his feet no longer obeyed his will, instead they carried him forward.

Though the Betweeners no longer owned any god or goddess, they still believed in a force for good and one for evil.  The Speakers had told of old days when certain strong people, both male and female, reached such heights of control that they could command even stones to move. Those were of yesteryear and few believed their like might even have lived.  Rather most Betweeners said inwardly that such were but creatures of legends cast into words by early Speakers to give the clans some fear of the unknown and thus limit their wandering.

"Essar, Roqued, Alsa..."  To drown out Modic's call or summons without words Rentam roared full throatedly those names of great bravery and supreme command.  He bent his mind toward the battle with raw fear, worked for the control of his body.  To that purpose he repeated the roll of Sacred Dead in a battle song.  The serpent thing was moving. It drew back its head, tensed muscles, and then ... Like a journey staff used as a lance, the head flashed toward Rentam .  By the thickness of a bavard leaf only did it miss seizing upon him.

Modic shrilled that cry a second time.  The sound got inside Rentam's head to cause a new kind of pain.

"Essar!"  he shouted back, or did he?

Was it true that he was answered, or merely that the tone and pitch of his voice cut through the sound spell Modic was weaving?  Rentam might never know.  Anymore than he could tell why and how the warmth in the broken length of colored fang ran up his arm, through him, banishing

Modic's influence.  Out of the far beginnings of his kind shot a thought that at first was a dim shadow, like a fear in night time, to set him moving.

"Alsa ..."  he said to himself.  Modic was being answered by another effort of the serpent creature.  Its head launched out a second time across the stream which divided them.  The open jaws hung poised above him, ready to seize.  Rentam braced himself.

Though the thing was near enough now that it could breathe upon him, there was no breath ... but a faint odor he had smelled many time before, Lacseed oil such as filled any lamp.

The jaws closed in as Rentam waited.  His hand swung up.  He thrust the butt end of the rod he had found into that open hollow in the jaw.  It settled there, fastened tightly, now a part of the dreadful set of fangs.

Then .. . there was a flash of orange and green, followed by streams of light.  The snakey head rose high.  It twisted.  Something shaped like a door broken open in its side.  One of the weighty feet snapped off.

The scent of oil was throat thickening as the creature threw itself backward, heaving and twisting violently.  A shudder and the fearsome head broke loose to fly through the air and smash against one of the chairs of the dead.  Bits of wire and small fragments of metal erupted out of the headless body.

That floundered forward into the stream.  For a moment or two the water boiled up about it in a mighty sweep of the current.  One of the great talons fl airing outward caught upon the board of buttons which Modic had fingered.  As the mutilated thing dropped, it drew that with it. There followed a flash so bright that Rentam cupped his hands-over smarting eyes, able to see nothing but the scarlet light.  But he heard.  This was no more wailing encouragement from the Seeker, rather explosions or giant crashs such as might come from the fall of a rock or of a great tree.

Another odor filled the stagnant air.  Rentam pressed the mask dizzily. What he smelled, what his tongue tasted was oil burning, but with that other stenches he could not name.  He rubbed his eyes.  The second lid there may have saved him from total blindness for he could see, hazily, yet enough to witness what had followed the destruction of the serpent-headed thing.

You could not say it was dead, for his senses still assured him that it had never lived.  But the great head had rolled along the edge of the pool.  Steam or mist arose from that sickeningly, making him flick his tongue back behind tight lips.  A dark smoke rolled along the passage which carried the flood out of the pool.  There were flames within that, burning with the same violent colors as had painted the sky when the first of the city's weapons had been launched.

Those flames were not alone.  The mummified bodies in the chairs each became a candle set alight by the boards they held.

From the heart of each of those pulsed tongues of fire, but these were white.

Modic still huddled in the chair.  His body writhed from side to side as if he were caught in a trap and was fighting feebly for freedom. The Seeker's face had changed, it was the countenance of a stranger, a stranger who could not believe in what was happening to him.  He

screamed a fountain of words, beating upon the arms of the chair with his fists.

The head of the snake thing had rolled to the foot of the first of the chairs.  From it still spilled oily liquid which quickly drew sparks of fire.  When the head thudded to a stop it was upright and those huge eyes stared at the funeral fire of the dead.

"Farguel!"

There was loss of all sanity in that whimper.  Modic leaned forward to the next chair, paying no attention to the smoldering body it still supported.

He spewed forth more words in an erratic pattern which held ghosts of the ritual sounds of a curse or incantation.  Then suddenly he stopped--his head shifted and he tried to raise his hands.

"Farguel..."

The head with a tangle of molten metal still trailing into the burning stream stared with its round eyes back at him.  Modic looked shriveled, empty, as he might have been one of the dead who shared his perch. Rentam tested the air once again.

That nameless will which he had felt--centering for a while in Modic--was gone.  The man was now what he had always been, a Seeker, sly, treacherous, greedy.  Only he was rapidly becoming less and less of a man.  Flooding out of him, even as the molten metal had flowed from the serpent's head, was that other--that strength which was not his but an unknown other's.

He used the arms of his chair to lever himself to his feet and stood gazing about the whole of this chamber as might a child who had awakened from a dark dream.  There was a looseness to his lips, his shoulders hunched as if he was awaiting some punishment.  He said, not looking towards Rentam, but as if he spoke to himself:

"He ... he is gone."  His hands clenched on the chest of his under robe.  The edge of it was scorched and there was a small trail of smoke coming from it.

"He is..."  now he shook his head as if to dislodge some insect.  For the first time he appeared to recognize Rentam and there was bemusement on both his face and in the way he staggered as he arose from the seat.

He leaned forward to stare down at the serpent, shivering.

"Farguel... there is no way ... no way!  They believe in the demons... we cleared the city so ... and then ..."  He paused, looked at the dying embers which had been the bodies.

"What do I say?"  Modic drew a hand across his face and let it fall limply to his side.

"I am not he ... but he remains in a little here."  Again his hand arose, to touch his head "To be a king... more than a king ... to rule a world.  That he might have done...."  Then Modic lapsed into silence.

For the first time Rentam spoke, "Who was he, Seeker?"

"He was--one who waited--and waited--from our beginnings they came, all of them."  He raised his hand a little to indicate the remains in the other chairs.

"They made Farguel."  His voice was stronger, as if some small thread of another still curled in his mind.

"They would be rulers here and he was the greatest among them. But when those they awaited did not come, they put barriers about the cities they had taken and sat to wait.  How long did you wait?"

He addressed, the nearest chair as if that still held a living man.

"Too long, too long.  They said then that they would set up the final guards and sleep as they sometimes did when they traveled among the stars.  So it was decided.  But not by him!  He went hunting always, hunting for that which would awaken the rest, take from them dreams of

stars that they would learn of this world and what could be done here.

"He sent out power to poison the land, to be another barrier behind which he remained to labor... ."

Another pause.  Modic dug his fists hard against his temples.

"Why do I remember, tell me that, Guide?  He holds... still he holds... and he will... No."  Before Rentam could move, Modic, his voice shrilling upward, as it had during his frenzy of his possession, threw himself down and out.  His body struck against the disintegrating head of the thing he had called Farguel.  He did not scream again as he slid on and out into the fire which flowed with the stream.

Rentam retreated swiftly to the far wall of the hall, then leaped toward the entrance of the corridor.  As if the death of Modic was the last fuel, flames flared behind, reaching so that he had to beat the fire from the edge of his cloak.  But that other will... that power which had measured him so hungrily was gone.  There was no life any longer in this place.

The guide reached the outermost part of the great palace or temple. Flames sped in waves along the sluggish stream.  Only that light which had touched the sky was gone.  Here was only a dry emptiness, an absence of all life within the ruin.

That which Rentam had sensed as shadows of terror was also gone.  He stood, his chest heaving from his run.  All the stream was now afire.

He glanced back just once at the palace from which he had escaped.  His tongue flicked out... all life was not gone.  There was a whinny.  The horse showed himself within the core of a long gone building, picking his way toward the guide.  Rentam's mind filled with surprise, then content.  He and this animal were alive.  The flame which destroyed the dead--the last of that was licking at the pool, flickering as what had fueled it was eaten up.

"Come."  The guide crossed to the horse who nuzzled at his shoulder and whinneyed louder than before. "Let us get out of this place, brother--for it is of long dead and should be left to them in peace."

He swung up into the saddle.  Willingly the horse turned without urging, pacing along that road which had led to the heart of Lonscraft.

Rentam would never understand all which had happened, but his flickering tongue assured him of safety--here was only tumbled stone, dust, and a sprung trap.  The destruction of the creature (he had to think of that as having life even though he could not sense it) and of the will of that other unknown which Modic had brought to half life, had perhaps reversed the poison of this dust-dry land and all it held. However let that be proven at some later time, by those who were born to be Seekers.  For himself now, he wanted no more of the Dry.  Thus he threaded a way between the masses of stone rubble until he passed beyond the gate of Lonscraft which once was.